Constance McLaughlin Green Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Constance McLaughlin Green Papers 1920-1969 (bulk 1953-1963)
MSS51292
Green, Constance McLaughlin, 1897-1975
22,000 items
17 containers plus 1 oversize
6.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Historian and author. Correspondence, drafts, galleys, and page proofs of writings, notes, printed and near-print material, clippings, speeches, and other papers relating primarily to Green's research on the history of Washington, D.C., and the publication of her two-volume Pulitzer Prize-winning book, Washington (1962-1963).
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bailey, Herbert Smith--Correspondence.; Brownlow, Louis, 1879-1963--Correspondence.; Crawford, M. D. C. (Morris De Camp), 1882-1949--Correspondence.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton), 1908-1980--Correspondence.; Franklin, John Hope, 1915-2009--Correspondence.; Green, Constance McLaughlin, 1897-1975.; Green, Constance McLaughlin, 1897-1975. Washington. 1962-1963.; Ihlder, John, 1876-1958--Correspondence.; Indritz, Phineas, 1916-1997--Correspondence.; James, Edward T.--Correspondence.; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974--Correspondence.; Robertson, David Allan, 1880-1961--Correspondence.
Organizations
Project Vanguard.
Subjects
African Americans--Washington (D.C.); Artificial satellites, American.; Astronautics--United States.; Cities and towns--United States.; City and town life--Connecticut--Naugatuck.; City and town life--Massachusetts--Holyoke.; Law--Washington (D.C.); Progress--Economic aspects.; Pulitzer Prizes.; Rockets (Aeronautics)
Places
Holyoke (Mass.)--History.; Naugatuck (Conn.)--History.; New England--Economic conditions.; United States--Economic conditions.; Washington (D.C.)--Economic conditions.; Washington (D.C.)--Economic policy.; Washington (D.C.)--History.; Washington (D.C.)--Politics and government.; Washington (D.C.)--Race relations.; Washington (D.C.)--Social conditions.; Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs.
Occupations
Authors.; Historians.
Provenance
The papers of Constance McLaughlin Green, historian and author, were given to the Library of Congress by Green in 1966 and 1970.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Constance McLaughlin Green are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1897, Aug. 21 Born, Ann Arbor, Mich.
1919 A.B., Smith College, Northampton, Mass.
1919 1920 Taught, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
1921 Married Donald Ross Green
1925 M.A., Mount Holyoke College, South Hadley, Mass.
1925 1932 Taught, Mount Holyoke College, South Hadley, Mass.
1937 Ph.D., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1939 1947 Taught, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.
1942 1945 Historian, Army Ordnance Department, Springfield, Mass.
1947 1948 Consulting historian, American Red Cross
1948 1951 Chief historian, Ordnance, Army History Division, Department of Defense
1951 1954 Historian, Research and Development Board, Office of the Secretary of Defense
1954 1960 Director, Washington, D.C., history project
1962 1963 Published Washington. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press. 2 vols.
1963 Awarded Pulitzer Prize
1975, Dec. 5 Died, Annapolis Md.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Constance McLaughlin Green (1897-1975) span the years 1920-1969, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period between 1953 and 1963 when Green researched and wrote her Pulitzer Prize-winning history of Washington, D.C. Published in 1962-1963 by Princeton University Press, the two-volume work, Washington, Village and Capital, 1800-1878 and Washington, Capital City, 1879-1950, was the product of a ten-year undertaking that Green completed with the aid of foundation grants and the administrative support of American University. The collection contains drafts and galleys of the work, voluminous research notes arranged according to the chronological blocks established by Green, and subject files that contain reports and correspondence pertaining to the editing and publishing of both volumes. Papers unrelated to the Washington project are limited to correspondence and to miscellaneous speeches and writings. The collection is organized into five series: Correspondence, Subject File, Speeches and Writings File, Research File, and Oversize.
As a historian and author, Green's career ranged from teaching positions at Mount Holyoke and Smith colleges to the post of chief historian, Ordnance, Army History Division, at the Department of Defense. Most noteworthy, however, was her pioneering insistence on the significance of the city in American history. Green's portrayal of the social reality of nineteenth and twentieth century urban life in Washington, D.C., can be traced in detail in the research notes in this collection. Together with her manuscript drafts, the note cards in these papers are a supplementary guide to the social practices, economic policies, racial attitudes, and political and legal standards that prevailed in the capital during its first one hundred fifty years. Absent from the papers are the transcripts or notes of interviews Green obtained from persons who lived in Washington during the years covered by the second volume. Brief recollections of a personal nature, however, are in the correspondence folder in the subject files of the Washington history project. Among those who offered their personal reminiscences of important episodes and conditions in the history of the city were Rayford Logan, Louis Brownlow, and Ulysses Simpson Grant (1864-1953).
Other writings in the collection include her doctoral dissertation published as Holyoke, Massachusetts; A Case History of the Industrial Revolution in America (New Haven, Yale University Press, 1939.). Also in the writings are speeches on such diverse themes as “Project Vanguard” and New England's contribution to America's economic progress. Additional items include notes and drafts of journal articles; notes and related material for her published book on urban history relating to Naugatuck, Connecticut; manuscripts of encyclopedia entries on the subject of Washington, D.C.; and a book review of Morton and Lucia White's The Intellectuals Versus the City.
Correspondence on subjects other than Washington, D.C., is slight. Important exceptions are letters from Charles A. Lindbergh concerning the manuscript of a book Green coauthored with Milton Lomask entitled Vanguard; A History (Washington, D.C.: Scientific and Technical Information Division, National Aeronautics and Space Administration, 1970) for which Lindbergh wrote an introduction, and a small group of letters relating to Green's advisory role in the publication of Notable American Women.
Correspondents include Herbert Smith Bailey, Louis Brownlow, M. D. C. Crawford, Charles B. Fahs, John Hope Franklin, Phineas Indritz, John Ihlder, Edward T. James, and David Allan Robertson.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Correspondence, 1942-1969
Subject File, 1945-1964
Speeches and Writings File, 1920-1969
Research File: Washington
Oversize
Container List
- Correspondence, 1942-1969 (Box 1)
  Letters received.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of sender or subject of correspondence.
  - General, 1942, 1950, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Lindbergh, Charles A., concerning Vanguard; a History, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Notable American Women, publication of, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
- Subject File, 1945-1964 (Box 1)
  Clippings, printed matter, press releases, copies and extracts of documents, notes, reports, minutes, charts, tables, correspondence, and miscellaneous near-print matter used in the Washington, D.C., history project or received as a consequence of winning the Pulitzer Prize.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material or subject.
  - Washington, D.C., history project (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and comments on the manuscript, 1953-1963 (Box 1)
    - District of Columbia incorporation charts (Box 1)
    - Notes, charts, and copies and extracts of documents (Box 1)
    - Press releases for Washington, vol. 2, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Project reports, advisory committee minutes, and miscellany, 1955-1962 (Box 1)
    - Pulitzer Prize, 1963 (Box 1)
      - Clippings and near-print announcement (Box 1)
      - Letters of congratulations, 1963 (Box 1)
      - Notification letters and award (Box 1)
    - Race and segregation in Washington, D.C., annotated printed and near-print matter, 1945-1950 (Box 1)
    - Tables with holograph annotations, for use in publication (Box 1)
- Speeches and Writings File, 1920-1969 (Box 1-7)
  Holograph, typewritten, and near-print notes and manuscripts of Green's speeches and writings. Also original, revised, amended, and annotated versions of near-print and typewritten drafts of Green's Washington, as well as corrected galleys and marked page proofs of the same work.
  Organized into a general file arranged alphabetically by title or topic and a Washington file arranged generally in the order in which the work was advanced to publication.
  - General (Box 2)
    - “The Case of Project Vanguard,” speech, Society on History of Technology, 1969 (Box 2)
    - “Civil Rights in the District of Columbia, 1862-1953,” incomplete, undated (Box 2)
    - The development of cities, speech, Georgetown University, Washington, .D.C., Urban History Conference, 1969 (Box 2)
    - “History of Holyoke, Massachusetts, a Case History of the Industrial Revolution in America,” doctoral dissertation, Yale University, New Haven, Conn., 1937 (Box 2)
    - History of Naugatuck, Connecticut, by Green, notes and related material, 1920-1950 (Box 2)
    - Industrial situation in New England, correspondence, notes, and partial draft, 1950 (Box 2)
    - The Intellectual Versus the City: From Thomas Jefferson to Frank Lloyd Wright, by Morton and Lucia White, book review, 1963 (Box 2)
    - “The Jacksonian 'Revolution' in the District of Columbia,” 1959 (Box 2)
    - “New England's Changing Pattern,” 1950 (Box 2)
    - New England's Contribution to American Economic Life, radio talk, 1944 (Box 2)
    - Seattle, Washington, notes for a lecture, 1950 (Box 2)
    - “United States Ordnance Department, World War II and Earlier,” speech, American Historical Association, 1949 (Box 2)
    - “Washington's Double Life,” 1964 (Box 2)
    - “Washington,” encyclopedia articles, 1960, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Washington: the ideal and the reality, lecture, Goucher College, Baltimore, Md., 1963 (Box 2)
  - Washington (Box 2)
    - Near-print drafts, (4 folders); (15 folders); (2 folders) (Box 2, Box 3, Box 4)
    - Revised drafts, (16 folders); (2 folders) (Box 4, Box 5)
    - Original and amended drafts, vol. 2, (22 folders) (Box 5)
    - Galley proofs, with corrections (Box 6)
      - Vol. 1, (4 folders) (Box 6)
      - Vol. 2, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 6, Box 7)
    - Page proofs, marked for indexing, vol. 2, (4 folders) (Box 7)
- Research File: Washington (Box 8-17)
  Note cards of research material for the writing of Washington.
  Arranged in chronological units with some additional divisions between information collected on the white and black communities in the city.
  - 1800-1812 (Box 8)
  - 1818-1829 (Box 9)
  - 1823-1846 (Box 9)
  - 1823-1846 (Box 10)
  - 1848-1850 (Box 10)
  - 1848-1850 (Box 11)
  - 1861-1871 (Box 11)
  - 1861-1871 (Box 12)
  - 1874-1878 (Box 13)
  - 1878-1901 (Box 13)
  - 1878-1901 (Box 14)
  - Negro, 1878-1917 (Box 15)
  - White, 1901-1917 (Box 15)
  - White, 1901-1917 (Box 16)
  - 1917-1930 (Box 16)
  - 1920-1950 (Box 17)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  District of Columbia Corporation charts.
  Described according to the series and container from which the charts were removed.
  - Subject file (Box OV 1)
    - Washington history project (Box OV 1)
      - District of Columbia corporation charts (Container 1) (Box OV 1)